<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>

<documentationdata>
	<documentation id="GettingStarted">
		<shortdesc>
			<lang-en>
				A Quick-Start Introduction to Scarab-Engine.
			</lang-en>
			<lang-fr>
				Bientôt ...
			</lang-fr>
		</shortdesc>
	
		<doccontent>
			<lang-en> There is allways a point to start from and here it is ! Let's dive into Scarab-Engine ...

				I/ General Things to Know

				    First things first, you need to be aware of a few behaviours used accross the whole engine to make
				sure you make proper use of the interfaces provided.
				
				    A/ Error Handling

				    Scarab-Engine is extremely picky and any invalid parameter or usage will spawn assertions at you and
				halt execution. Error recovery or abort behaviour is entirely yours to decide as long at it isn't an
				engine-level error which are allways asserted out. You can use the ErrorManager from the Lib module to
				handle and classify errors. The same goes for exceptions, if you want to use them, do it at your level.
				The engine itself doesn't use exceptions for obvious performance reasons ...
				The big advantage here is that if it works, then you know you've done it the right/best way. No complex
				though about is there a better/optimized to do this ... Only optimized stuff is available anyway !

				    B/ Managers

				    The whole engine is organized by modules and each module is represented in the code by a manager class.
				Managers are stand-alone singleton classes that holds the main hooks to the API. Each manager has its own
				tasks and capabilities and they are bound to each other by dependencies. For example, the Modeling manager
				builds and uses objects to be rendered, so it depends on the Rendering manager. Since there is a fair
				amount of managers, they also are separated by code-level layers.
				    All of these managers are accessible through a shortcut macro of the form '(name)Fn' with Fn being a
				suffix for 'Function'. So you want to do something about Rendering ? Use RenderingFn. About Modeling ? Use
				ModelingFn. Want a math function ? Use MathFn. And so on ... Easy enough !
				    The lowest level managers are in the Third-Party module including the very important SystemFn that gives
				you a consistent and platform-independent API for system operations such as file IO, network IO, threading,
				etc ... At this level you can also find special managers that are not exposed by the engine end-user API.
				Those are wrappers to the various third-party API that we have to rely on. I tried to keep their number
				as small as possible but there are ones we just have to use (OS APIs, DirectX/OpenGL, CUDA, ...).
				    On the second layer is the Lib module and all its definitions. Here you will find all standard libraries
				you could expect: data structures, math, strings, objects, ... Two managers are of special importance here.
				The ErrorManager allows you to define error contexts and values and manage them in a way that allows easy
				logging and referencing. The engine itself only uses strict assertions but the top-level user can of course
				make more forgiving error recovery management using this. The MemoryManager manages ... memory ! This is
				probably the most important and usage-intensive one so we will discuss it in its own section just below.
				    On the third layer is the Engine module itself and all the important managers like RenderingManager,
				GUIManager,	PhysicsManager, ...
				This is where most of the work is done and you will uses these managers	heavily.
				The WorldManager is of particular importance since it is your scene representation interface to
				put game entities into. Each object in this world can then be assigned a rendering representation and an
				animation representation, respectively crafted using the ModelingManager and PhysicsManager. Take a note
				here that all animation features are in the PhysicsManager. Kinematic controllers like keyframes are there
				to integrate scripted animation inside the physical world smoothly.
				The Application manager may be considered on layer '3.5' as it is a little above all other managers in the
				Engine module in abstraction. Its purpose is to merge all the engine and lower level parts into one hook
				to expose a base interface for application frameworks.
				    Lastly, the fourth layer is the 'user-level' layer and stands above the whole engine so everything is
				available to build an application. There is no master header though and you must take care to include exactly
				what you need. Still, managers do have master headers and some key files like System.h, MemoryManager.h or
				other managers will provide you all-in-one inclusion. You can go both ways here and use an hybrid approach by
				including master module headers for things you use intensively and pick extra support for what you exactly
				need using specific include files. This is a great way to build your own customized 'master header'.
				The Basic Framework discussed later in the documentation is implemented in this layer.

				    C/ Memory budgets

				    Memory in Scarab-Engine is handled in a very controlled way. In fact you don't even have the right to
				allocate memory yourself ! malloc/free, HeapAlloc/HeapFree or C++ new/delete are all banned ! The engine
				uses them internally and you don't want to mess with that, do you ? To provide almost constant-time dynamic
				memory allocation, the engine pre-allocates big chunks of memory and gives them to each manager as a workspace.
				Each manager has a set of memory chunks which is called its memory budget. This concept is very important
				since you will have to precisely adjust them to fit your application consumption. You can monitor the memory
				easily using the manager's tracing and reporting systems. A release build will want them as small and tight
				fitting as possible while a debugging environment will want them large enough so there is not to worry about
				them anymore.
				    Memory budgets are found in each engine's inline (.inl) file, this will soon be moved to the configuration
				module and loaded from a file. Sizes are given in bytes. Note that for the RenderingManager, this only applies
				to system memory, video memory is never exposed and is dealt with inside the engine.
				You should see the memory budget declarations have three properties : A label name, an allocation type and a
				pool size in bytes. A memory chunk is uniquely identified by its owning manager and its label name.
				The allocation type describes the type of allocator to use for this memory chunk, it can be either break, stack,
				pool or heap. Heap is the default and the most generic but also the slowest, a good memory budget uses stacks
				(fixed allocation ordering) and pools (fixed allocation size) as much as possible. The break allocator is an
				old-fashioned assembler-like memory chunk breaker, it is very fast, very manual and very unsafe, use it at your
				own risk ... (it was removed for now, will be back with some security improvements).
				    Note that all managers have a "Scratch" memory chunk to be used for temporary data, this is a good place to
				use a stack for example ... Note there is also a special memory budget bound to no manager in particular, called
				the shared memory context. It can be selected for occasional interactions with out-of-context data regarding
				memory and for multi-thread communication.
				    I have those memory budgets ok ... now what ? Hmm ... you use the engine's operators of course ! You have,
				just like C++, three operators given to you in the form of macros : 'New', 'Delete()' and 'DeleteA()' to fill
				the respective roles and behaviour of new, delete and delete[]. Simple ... but you also need a way to specify
				the budget you want to use ! This is done using the memory context stack.
				    The MemoryManager maintains a stack of each memory chunk that has been selected/unselected. A memory context
				is opened when you select a memory chunk using a manager's '->SelectMemory("BudgetName")' method and closed when
				you unselect it using that same	manager's '->UnSelectMemory()' method. These acts like Push/Pop operations on
				the memory context stack.
				    The 'New', 'Delete()' and 'DeleteA()' operators will act on memory relative to the memory context selected
				in the current code block (ie the memory context at the top of the stack). Note that the MemoryManagers pushes
				the shared memory context as the first bottom-most context in the stack and the ApplicationManager then adds its
				Scratch context on top of it. Those must never be unpushed manually.
				    From here there is mainly two behaviours, you can either select a block for each memory operation or select
				once, do lots of operations, then unselect. Of course, you need to find the optimal balance between these two
				that best fits what you want to do, however, you should be warned that side effects happen when using unclosed
				contexts in objects methods, particularly constructors and destructors. Do not do this. Allways open and close
				your context inside the same method, this will avoid confusion too. Remember explicit is better than implicit.
				    A final remark about objects allocated by managers, they are managed by the manager and you don't need to
				worry about them. However this require you to strictly use each manager's factory functions, you should never
				allocate an engine object by yourself (except those made for derivation of course like GUI models). Each manager
				has its own Create* / Destroy* interface that gives access to all objects related to this manager. Those objects
				can in turn have such factory functions for other objects and so on ...
				    I know this can be a bit confusing and code-cluttering at first but it is a lot easier than it looks and it
				gives you a lot of freedom on memory along with a powerful abstraction for allocators and segmentation.
				You will never need to pass allocation-related data to anything as long as it is implemented in the context of a
				manager ... which is the case for everything in the engine. On the bonus side you have integrated memory tracing
				and reporting with logging and you have a great way to track bugs you find at the 'memory corrupted' stage.

				    D/ Math conventions

				    Maths in Scarab-Engine are simple : we use the same conventions as real maths ! If ever in doubt, read this
				again and you have your answer. Well some precisions about computer ... precision. Though.
				The engine uses a generic template math library that can be used with all fundamental number formats defined in
				Lib/Math/Formats. In addition to the built-in float and double formats, we define Scalar at compile-time to be
				either float or double and represent the engine's default precision mode. Fixed format represents fixed-precision
				arithmetics, Integer format represents infinite precision integers and Rational format represents exact	rational
				arithmetics. By default Scalar is bound to float.
				On top of those, Types are defined for various non-scalar math objects like vectors, matrices, colors, ...
				All matrix operations are row based, matrices are stored by row and vectors are viewed as columns. All vector
				operations use right hans side convention (ie TrVector2 = Matrix32 * Vector3). This way the first index is
				allways the row index, then column index, ...
				    The MathManager holds all basic math functions for arithmetics, analysis and geometry/trigonometry. You can
				set	various compile-time toggles here to enable tricks on some functions or switch between assembler, taylor,
				and other implementations.
				The math library is then split into various domains : Algebra, Analysis and Geometry mainly. A full description
				of all those is beyond the scope of this introduction and will be discussed in details in the developper manual.
				However you can browse the code easily and I'm sure you can figure out most of it just by reading the code.
				    Some specific stuff about rendering to clear things out though ...
				The engine uses Right Hand Side representation for frames and vector bases. View and projection transform are
				both RHS too of course. The Z-Axis should be the Up-Axis (not strictly enforced but you WILL confuse yourself).
				2D viewports are also RHS, with origin at the top-left corner, X-Axis going right, Y-Axis going down and Z-Axis
				going into the screen. Everything is RHS, That's it !

				II/ Using the Engine

				    When you download the project on the home page, you get a few important things. First, a text file giving
				installation instructions and Release notes. The root folder itself contains three main folders. '_VCProject'
				contains the Microsoft Visual C++ project files, 'Source' contains the engine source code and 'Working' contains
				the engine's run-time data, ie its working directory. This 'Working' folder also contains three main sub-folders,
				'Data', 'Logs' and 'Screenshots'. 'Data' contains important information the engine needs to be persistent like
				various states, configuration settings, scripts, resource databases, etc ... 'Logs' contains all logs generated
				by the error management system of the engine. And 'Screenshots' is a sample of a custom application folder used
				to store screenshots ...
				    After installing and opening the project in Microsoft Visual C++, use the solution explorer to navigate in
				the code and get your marks. Each module is compiled as a static library (dynamic library build is in project).
				Except for the EntryPoint module which contains a sample test application using the basic framework and is
				compiled as an executable.
				    In each main folder in the 'Engine' module you will find the manager's master header from which you can see
				the whole interface available to you for this manager. You just need to play with the objects then ...

				    A/ ResourceManager (ResourceFn) : Import and Export scene data in various formats

				    The ResourceManager is divided in two main parts : a persistent database and a resource format pipeline.
				The database (*.rdb files) is a self-contained filesystem using journalization and B+Tree based file allocation
				to provide optimized persistent storage and on-demand load/save for assets and resources. The ResourceManager
				gives interfaces to access data in a RDB database just like you would with a file.
				    Files in these databases can be of any arbitrary format as long as it is declared as a valid ResourceType.
				Those are the types supported by the resource pipeline. This pipeline handles data exchange operations between
				a database and external files, or between a database and loaded memory. This makes pre-loading resources very
				easy, you just need then to pass them to the renderer to load them into video memory and you're ready.
				Each resource type can have many formats (images-bmp/png/jpg ...) and the pipeline will be in constant evolution
				to support as many formats as possible, using a custom COLLADA-compliant format as the reference external
				representation and a custom binary engine-compliant format as the reference internal representation.
				Format conversion is transparent through the pipeline so you can input/output in any format you want.

				    B/ ModelingManager (ModelingFn) : Build geometry for scene objects

				    The ModelingManager is all about object crafting and geometry management. Here you will find objects to
				create and represent standard primitives, curves, surfaces, extrusions, or more complex compounds like LOD trees,
				CSG trees (in project), etc ...
				    I think this manager is pretty self-explaining ... no catch here. All primitives use standard conventions.
				See a primitive's header file, at the constructor's comment, to get details about vertices and facet layouts.

				    C/ RenderingManager (RenderingFn) : Rendering platform for scene objects

				    This is the visible part of your virtual world. Every object in the scene will have its rendering
				representation, if any, rendered using the parameters in this manager. This manager provides a lot of functions
				that can be further splitted into several parts : display modes management, render states management, viewport
				management, buffer clearing/color masking, camera management, rendering primitives, resource management, font
				management and cursor management. Quite a few ...
				Most of those concern standard rendering operations you should already be familiar with. However a few ones are
				worth a closer look. Also note that in this section, the term 'resource' refers to rendering resources specific
				to the RenderingManager.
				Render states can be set indirectly. We use an override system with two values : a base value and an override
				value. If the override value exists, it takes precedence over the base value. Any change to the base value is
				voided while the override value is active. This enables lots of tricks to ease render states switches.
				Camera management uses the Camera rendering resource. The manager gives you methods to create and destroy cameras
				and also to set the active rendering camera. Mouse ray-picking is also provided here.
				Rendering primitives includes the classic buffer-based primitive routine but it also provides a lot of batched
				procedures to help with fast 2D and text rendering among other things ...
				Rendering resources includes VertexFormat, VertexBuffer, IndexBuffer, Texture*, RenderTarget, VertexShader and
				PixelShader. These represent the low-level rendering mechanics and are not directly used, geometry related data
				is gathered into Mesh objects, rendering related data into Camera/RenderTarget/Light/Material/Texture objects
				and shader related data into ShaderProgram/ShaderParameters/ShaderConst. On top of those are the modeling manager
				handling Mesh objects and the Effect library of the RenderingManager dealing with lights, materials, textures and
				shaders ... All that being said you should know that rendering resources represent data that is actually copied
				to video memory and thus those objects must be bound to the manager and locked to access their memory.
				Precise management of those items in your scene is the key to performance ... (ie use instanciation a lot,
				preload anything you can). But you can do that from the top-level interfaces too of course.
				Lastly, font management includes loading/unloading but also basic functions for font and character properties and
				a very handy function for text-picking.

				    D/ PhysicsManager (PhysicsFn) : Animation platform for scene objects

				    This is the invisible part of your virtual world. Every object in the scene has its animation representation,
				if any, registered in this manager. This manager does a lot of things, it takes geometric representation of
				objects classified into shapes and provides real-time collision detection. Each shape is associated with a body
				that represents the physical properties of the object.
				Using results from collisions, the engine then animates each object according to the laws of constrained physics
				(Lagrange) using a constraint solver (A lot more details on those in the Developper Manual). You can also use a
				kinematic controller to enforce your own scripted animation to an object (key-frames, paths, ...).
				    A few indications on the structure of this world. The physical world is basically a graph with nodes and edges,
				where nodes represent objects while edges represent constraints or relations. From this you deduce that bodies
				are nodes ... yes that's it. But there are several types of bodies: rigid bodies for dynamic animation, kinematic
				bodies for kinematic animation or soft bodies for soft dynamics animation. You also have systems of bodies like
				particle systems, ragdolls or skeletons.
				    About edges, they are a few too. Contact edges are special and you don't control them as they exist only when
				a contact is being solved. Contacts are non-persistent constraints. Joints, on the other hand, are persistent
				constraints and describe axis-specific translation and rotation constraints between either an object and the
				world or between two objects. A ragdoll is a composition of rigid bodies and joints.
				    Controllers, on the kinematic side, are quite different. A controller applies a scripted or pre-computed
				animation to a kinematic body. Only the special BlendController blends the animation between two other controllers.
				Controllers do not usually 'connect' objects like joints do, however there is an exception : the IKJointController
				which represents a joint constraint but in a kinematic form. A skeleton is a composition of kinematic bodies and
				ikjoint controllers.
				    Systems are a little more complex, because of deformable shapes handling. This part is left to further study
				in the Developper Manual.

				    E/ WorldManager (WorldFn) : Assemble your scene objects

				    To centralize all the data needed in a virtual environment, a scene manager is mandatory. A good manager has
				multiple objectives : provide easy scene manipulation and hierarchic object representation and integrate side
				functions like visibility culling, ray casting, debug drawing, cameras, lights and global effects such as shadows
				and reflection. This is exactly what you will find here. The scene is organized as a tree where each node is a
				logical container and each leaf is a scene object. Leaves can have mesh and bodies attached to them to provide
				both rendering and animation representations. Nodes can have many uses, you have container nodes like BSP nodes
				or Switch nodes, etc ...
				    A particular attention here about the indoor and outdoor scene systems.
				The indoor system, first, uses portals to compute visible rooms in a room graph. An indoor scene is composed of
				several 'convex room' objects, organized in a BSP tree using 'indoor area' objects. Each 'convex room' object can
				be assigned 'portal' objects pointing to another target 'convex room' object to materialize an oriented 'doorway'
				between	the rooms (note I said oriented, usually you want the other room to have a portal to the first one too).
				Also a special 'portal culler' object must be used to compute visibility for an indoor scene.
				See the example MyDungeon.h in the EntryPoint test module of the release package.
				The outdoor system is quite simpler and only consists of a grid of areas which in turn are grids of regions. Each
				region is a rectangular section of the landscape and uses an height-map as geometry data. Visibility is computed
				using a simple view distance estimation and regions are dynamically loaded/unloaded/refreshed using a cache.

				    F/ GUIManager (GUIFn) : Build user interfaces

				    You have your scene and everything but it looks too static ... user interaction to the rescue ! Scarab-Engine
				provides a fully-featured GUI to help you build wonderful interfaces using all standard widgets. The GUI is
				event-driven and follows the MVC model. This basically means that for any graphical object you want on the screen
				you will need a window as a primary container and a widget to represent your object. The GUI itself is a collection
				of windows, each one being a tree of widgets.
				    Widgets can be used to show data (Labels, Lists, ...), to take input (InputText, CheckBox, Button, ...) or both.
				To use a widget you want two things : access the widgets events to do what you want and have some control over the
				widget's appearence. In a MVC model, both of those can be achieved easily. A widget is in fact composed of two
				classes, one that represents the widget itself containing the drawing method (the view), and another one that
				contains both methods to retrieve the appearence of the widget (the model) and callback methods to control what
				happen when the user does something to the widget (click a button, etc ...).
				    Another important aspect of the GUI is the layout. Positionning and sizing properties of widgets are controlled
				using layout objects that basically give rules on a method to deduce the properties of a widget from the properties
				of its parent container and a set of given parameters. The region computed by a layout for its widget is called the
				widget's client area or client rect. All widgets are in the client rect of something above, the top	level being a
				window. On the opposite of widgets, windows don't have any hierarchy between them.
				    Another type of element exists along windows and widgets : overlays. Overlays are used to represent on-screen
				elements such as context menus or tooltips ... Those act mostly like a mix between a window and a widget, they
				behave like top-most windows but instead of containing a tree of widgets, they have a stand-alone function as if
				they were a widget themselves.
				    Last but not least, the GUI will need you to feed him application events manually, because you might want to
				not	use it ! So this is done easily by just forwarding event parameters in the application's class's callbacks to
				the	GUIManager's callbacks and you're good. However, you do not want to mix dealing event in both that application's
				callbacks and the GUI's callbacks this would be a mess, even worse with multi-threading ...
				In order to handle events that are not handled by the GUI again, the manager provides the backboard class, a
				special widget that	represents ... a virtual backboard ! Any event that ends up being 'unfocused' (ie no destination
				widget) or unhandled by any window or overlay is sent to this backboard as an event that was not dealt with but
				might still	need attention. The backboard itself is an allways present widget and cannot be modified, however its
				model can be dynamically changed.
				    For common usage you will typically derivate your own model from the widget's model overriding appearence
				functions to control the view and overriding event callbacks to handle the controller. Then you will use an instance
				of your class to build the widget and lastly add that widget to your GUI tree using an appropriate layout.
				You will also want to register your own derivate model for the backboard, to handle unfocused events.
				The console manager described below is a good sample of a basic interface design.

				    G/ ConsoleManager (ConsoleFn) : Automate things using scripts

				    If you know a bit about coding, you know one of the most precious talent of an excellent programmer is ...
				His/Her's lazyness ! We are all lazy and we want to be. So much that we want to be 'optimal' in lazyness.
				That means we have to get smart about doing the fewest things we can and this is where it becomes an art.
				    Scripting is probably the best example of such lazyness in the programming world, in fact almost anything that
				do not require you to solve a complex math problem can be scripted. It's all a matter of layers. The more layers
				of abstraction you have, the more complex problem you handle with ease, the more complex tasks you can achieve.
				    The modular architecture of the engine itself is an example of this regarding code design. But here we want
				more. We want to be able to drive the engine at runtime and 'call' its API in an interactive shell ... A console.
				    This opens a complete world of awesomeness since through this the whole engine becomes interactive and you can
				virtually, but tediously, do anything. The tedious part will be removed using a nice and rich editor GUI ...
				    The console has its own environment where you can create generic variables to hold any kind of object handled
				by the engine. Add a simple /run command to execute a sequence of console commands from a file and you have	basic
				scripting in the engine ! This is extremely useful ... think of what you can do here about modeling, GUI building,
				scene setups, etc ...
				    A basic script that lists all available commands in a naive way is in the release package under /Working/Data
				/Scripts/Console. You can run it using '/run CmdList'. Use the '/help' command in the console to get specific help
				about commands.

				    H/ ApplicationManager (ApplicationFn) : Putting it all together

				    Once you have all the parts understood, it is time to make it all work together using the ApplicationManager.
				This manager is here to provide you with two classes : ConsoleApplication and WindowApplication to handle both
				text-based and graphical-based applications. All you need to do is to create a class that will represent your
				application and derivate it from either of those two classes.
				    In fact, this will give you more work to do to override all minimal callbacks you need to handle your application
				properly but it also abstracts you from the	system-dependent entry point (main function) and takes care of basic
				system handling (event loop, graphic context, ...). From there you have Callbacks for anything you need, more details
				will follow in the basic framework section of the documentation.

				III/ Conclusion

				    Congratulations ! You now know enough about the engine to start coding on very good bases. You should try
				and experiment all those concepts with the test application in the release package to get a feeling of what
				you do. You can also read the Basic Framework section for further information about the top-level API's basic
				operations and code samples.
				    However before you start some serious code, I strongly advise you to read the Coding Conventions section.
				It is boring I know but it is the only way to have everyone agree on the same behaviour to write consistent
				code and limit refactoring headaches.
					
				    Once again, the forum is your friend, you have an undocumented problem ? Just ask me, I'll answer as fast
				as I can ! Thank you for reading this documentation, see you on the forum !
			</lang-en>
			<lang-fr>
				Bientôt ...
			</lang-fr>
		</doccontent>
	
	</documentation>
</documentationdata>

